Matt Orcutt

Profile

I am a proven product designer who has delivered engaging digital experiences for in both enterprise and startup environments. My passions revolves around innovating interaction design, coaching/collaborating design strategy, even digging into the code, but mostly its finding beauty through simplicity.

Contact

morcutt@gmail.com mattorcutt.com 330.232.4601 linkedin.com/in/mttrctt twitter.com/morcutt

Core Competency

Product Strategy
User Research
Information Architecture
Interaction Design
Front End Dev

Interests

Data Visualization Machine Learning AI Fine Art

Tools

Adobe Suite
Sketch
Invision
Axure
HTML / CSS
A11y
Javascript
React
Git
Node

Education

Ruby

Ohio University BFA, Studio Painting 1994 – 1998 BFA, Art Education 1994 – 1998

Employment Experience

Sr UX Design Lead

 \bigcirc

IBM Watson Health, Cleveland Ohio

May 2018 to Present

In my current role lead research and design in creating next generation analytic tools for provider administrators. My responsibility is innovating ways multi hospital healthcare system executives can view their clinical and financial performance against national benchmarks without having to reconcile data from multiple dashboards. Employing information architecture, discoverability as well as data visualization strategies are key experience dimensions we track for. Partnering closely with analytics, product and development teams I managed design resources to research and test ideas that included AI and machine learning.

Manager, UX Design Lead

IBM Watson Health, Cleveland Ohio

June 2015 to May 2018

I was responsible for hiring and growing a cross functional design team of UX designers, researchers and front end developers. I functioned as a player/coach and mentored lean UX and design system methodologies across multiple offerings and their integration into IBM Watson Health.

In this role I was responsible for the design of IBM Explorys products while also developing the strategic design of new offerings related to on-boarding Electronic Health Record data into the Watson Health Data Fabric. Our clients sit on massive and disparate data sets they have across multiple hospital systems and providing speed to value is paramount to unlocking this data's potential to helping improve people's health and quality of life. I organized with my team to use design thinking to research and test a next generation data as a service platform. This included Data Scientist tooling for administrative configuration, data flow dashboards, project management dashboards, and ELT tooling integration.

Manager, UX Design Lead

Explorys, Cleveland Ohio

February 2013 to June 2015

In this role was responsible for design of Explorys products which provided multi hospital healthcare system administrators understand their value based care populations and target performance improvement opportunities for their physicians. I was their first design hire, built out the design program and hired a small team that helped shift development from functionality project focus to a user centered design product focus. I acted as a player/coach leading design from research to production on multiple product enhancements including overall product rebranding, next generation patient summaries, cohort creation VBC dashboards and data lineage visualizations.

Matt Orcutt

Contact

morcutt@gmail.com mattorcutt.com 330.232.4601 linkedin.com/in/mttrctt twitter.com/morcutt

Lead Front End Developer

January 2009 to February 2013

Within3. Cleveland Ohio

Ò

I was recruited as the lead front end developer and designer redesign the platform and create a flexible design system for a template based platform. Within3 is redefining advisory boards for pharmaceutical companies by deploying it in a virtual. It was important to allow physicians who use the system to find it delightful and easy to contribute their response content at their leisure. Client administrators as well needed to be able to spin up and manage multiple instances with custom component priority and branding. This resulted in the creation of a development kit that would allow clients to create and customize theirs sites themselves with a robust design system supporting it.

UX Designer

February 2008 to January 2009

Progressive, Cleveland Ohio

In this role I was responsible to design and testing new workflow functionality that would allow progressive client service representative to use as see the same interface as consumers. The progressive direct group was responsible to empowering consumers to manage their own policies including adding new vehicles and drivers we well as requesting proof of insurance. With a complete redesign of their internal system Progressive wanted to better support their customer service phone reps by giving them the same interface as the consumer with added administration abilities. I was successful in increasing a 25% conversion success when consumers were switching between multiple policies.

The Karcher Group

September 2001 to February 2008

Sr.Multimedia Designer/Developer, Canton Ohio

It was the Karcher Group is where I cut my teeth on web design and development. TKG is a boutique web design and SEO company that serves hundreds of clients. My role was to design and build out e commerce sites that were organically SEO friendly using an in house CMS system. This was the earlier days of the web and web standards and CSS were just being created as I got started. It was here where I learned most of my philosophy of web development that still hold today around the importance of web standards, progressive enhancements, and accessibility. These things were apparent to anyone who has tried to develop good design in netscape 4.